BLOODY HEART
قلب دموي
THE PEOPLE, GROUPS, PLACES, AND INCIDENTS IN THIS DRAMA ARE PURELY FICTIONAL
الأشخاص والمجموعات والأماكن والحوادث في هذه الدراما خيالية حقًا
Are you saying…
هل تقول…
you would rather be my enemy?
تفضل أن تكون عدوي؟
When you of all people
عندما كنت من كل الناس
are aware of how my life has been?
تدركون كيف كانت حياتي؟
When I am finally close to strengthening
عندما اقتربت أخيرًا من التعزيز
the royal authority--
السلطة الملكية--
There will be no end to it.
لن يكون هناك نهاية لذلك.
That is why I chose this path.
لهذا اخترت هذا الطريق.
No.
رقم.
No, you are to stop.
لا ، عليك أن تتوقف.
You must stop.
يجب أن تتوقف.
If you choose to stand against me,
إذا اخترت الوقوف ضدي ،
I will…
أنا سوف…
have to eliminate you.
يجب أن يقضي عليك.
I wanted power desperately
كنت أرغب بشدة في السلطة
only to protect you.
فقط لحمايتك.
I did not want to lose my wife in vain just as my late father did.
لم أكن أريد أن أفقد زوجتي سدى كما فعل والدي الراحل.
I shall
على أن
continue on my path. It is the only way to protect you.
أكمل في طريقي.  إنها الطريقة الوحيدة لحمايتك.
Please do so, Your Majesty.
من فضلك افعل ذلك يا جلالة الملك.
Go down your own path.
اذهب في طريقك الخاص.
However,
لكن،
take that journey for yourself, and not for my sake.
خذ هذه الرحلة لنفسك وليس من أجلي.
I will
أنا سوف
protect myself.
احمي نفسي.
I will protect myself…
سأحمي نفسي ...
with everything I have.
مع كل ما لدي.
BLOODY HEART FINAL EPISODE
الحلقة النهائية للقلب الدموي
What do you mean?
ماذا تقصد بذلك؟
The consort is Yoo Haksoo's daughter, the deposed crown princess?
القرين هي ابنة يو هاكسو ، ولي العهد المخلوع؟
That is correct.
هذا صحيح.
What will happen to Councilor Park
ماذا سيحدث لـ Councilor Park
if that is true?
إذا كان هذا صحيحا؟
His crime is too dire.
جريمته رهيبة للغاية.
Why did you make such a foolish choice?
لماذا اتخذتم مثل هذا الاختيار الأحمق؟
If I didn't shake around His Majesty's design,
إذا لم أهتز حول تصميم جلالة الملك ،
all members of Sarim and the Royal Court
جميع أعضاء ساريم والديوان الملكي
would have been pushed around by him.
تم دفعه من قبله.
I do not know what your deal with the consort was,
أنا لا أعرف ما هو اتفاقك مع الرفيق ،
but you'll regret this.
لكنك ستندم على هذا.
I think through every choice I make so that I do not regret anything.
أعتقد أنه من خلال كل خيار أقوم به حتى لا أندم على أي شيء.
Respectfully escort him to the State Tribunal.
مرافقته بكل احترام إلى محكمة الدولة.
-Yes, my lord.
-نعم سيدي.  -نعم سيدي.
What did I want to do with power?
ماذا أردت أن أفعل بالسلطة؟
Nothing.
لا شئ.
I only hoped to protect.
كنت أتمنى فقط أن أحمي.
The one thing that made the ones I missed return and visit
الشيء الوحيد الذي جعل من فاتني العودة والزيارة
was power.
كانت القوة.
Let us go.
دعنا نذهب.
Your Highness. And also Mother.
صاحب السمو.  وكذلك الأم.
How could you do something this serious?
كيف يمكنك فعل شيء بهذه الخطورة؟
I have no excuses.
ليس لدي أعذار.
You shouldn't dare to rebuke the consort.
لا يجب أن تجرؤ على توبيخ الزوجة.
This is something your father and I did.
هذا شيء فعلناه أنا ووالدك.
Mother.
الأم.
My lord has kept his promise.
ربي قد أوفى بوعده.
It's now your turn.
حان دورك الآن.
You must keep your promise to keep our family
يجب أن تفي بوعدك بالحفاظ على عائلتنا
and Councilor Park safe.
و Councilor Park آمن.
I shall do that.
سأفعل ذلك.
I will trust your words.
سوف أثق في كلماتك.
The consort was the former crown princess?
هل كانت القرينة ولي العهد السابق؟
What does that mean?
ماذا يعني ذلك؟
You must calm down, Lady Cho.
يجب أن تهدأ يا سيدة تشو.
She had committed such a grave crime.
لقد ارتكبت مثل هذه الجريمة الخطيرة.
Why won't you discuss her punishment?
لماذا لا تناقش عقوبتها؟
Didn't I tell you?
الم اقل لك
Even His Majesty turned a blind eye to it.
حتى جلالة الملك غض الطرف عنها.
Father.
أب.
We cannot bring down the consort.
لا يمكننا إسقاط الرفيق.
But Councilor Park is over.
لكن كونسيلور بارك قد انتهى.
Stay low.
ابقى منخفضا.
You are to be the queen, but you have not been installed yet.
أنت ستكون الملكة ، لكنك لم تثبت بعد.
And His Majesty is
وجلالة الملك
capable of deposing you even after you become one.
قادر على عزلك حتى بعد أن تصبح واحدًا.
Aren't you happy?
الا انت سعيد
I'm scared.
أنا خائف.
Father and Brother. Do you wish for me to become queen?
الأب والأخ.  هل تتمنى ان اصبح ملكة؟
You can only survive in the palace
يمكنك البقاء على قيد الحياة فقط في القصر
only if you have His Majesty's favor or power.
فقط إذا كان لديك صالح أو سلطة جلالة الملك.
What I'm the most afraid of is that you might end up
أكثر ما أخاف منه هو أن ينتهي بك الأمر
growing old all alone.
يكبرون بمفردهم.
The consort is afraid I'll take the path of the deposed king
القرين خائف من أن أسير في طريق الملك المخلوع
and his queen.
وملكته.
Do you
هل أنت
also believe I'll walk down that path?
أعتقد أيضا أنني سوف أسير في هذا الطريق؟
No matter which path you take,
بغض النظر عن المسار الذي تسلكه ،
the path you choose is the right one.
المسار الذي تختاره هو الطريق الصحيح.
You are
أنت
always stronger than me.
دائما أقوى مني.
I am nothing but a lowly man.
أنا لست سوى رجل وضيع.
This lowly servant was taken in and taught to be useful,
تم أخذ هذا العبد المتواضع وتعليمه ليكون مفيدًا ،
then I was freed from my servanthood and acknowledged
ثم تحررت من عبودي واعترف بي
only by the late King.
فقط من قبل الملك الراحل.
And the late King said
وقال الملك الراحل
I was the only one he could trust.
كنت الوحيد الذي يمكنه الوثوق به.
He asked me to look after you.
طلب مني أن أعتني بك.
I have seen the humiliation of the late King,
لقد رأيت إذلال الملك الراحل ،
and I saw the devastating death of his queen.
ورأيت الموت المدمر لملكته.
I cannot let you go in misery too.
لا استطيع ان ادعك تذهب في البؤس ايضا.
Please do not waver.
من فضلك لا تتردد.
Call in the Three Offices.
اتصل بالمكاتب الثلاثة.
The least I can do… is warn her.
أقل ما يمكنني فعله ... هو تحذيرها.
My father is Scholar Yoo Haksoo,
والدي هو الباحث يو هاكسو ،
and I am his daughter.
وانا ابنته.
My father and I have our foundation in the Sarim.
أبي وأنا لدينا مؤسستنا في صريم.
I am one with all of you.
انا واحد معكم جميعا
Therefore, please join me.
لذلك ، يرجى الانضمام إلي.
We shall do that.
سنفعل ذلك.
We were unfairly framed and banished to the wild,
لقد تم تأطيرنا بشكل غير عادل ونفينا إلى البرية ،
unable to even breathe at ease as criminals.
غير قادر حتى على التنفس براحة كمجرمين.
Yes, you were chased down as a traitor,
نعم ، لقد تم ملاحقتك كخائن ،
then you came to this place all alone.
ثم أتيت إلى هذا المكان بمفردك.
We will do everything in our power
سنفعل كل ما في وسعنا
to make you the queen and your son, the prince.
لتجعلك الملكة وابنك الأمير.
Thank you.
شكرًا لك.
-Thank you for your grace.
-شكرا لك على نعمتك.  -شكرا لك على نعمتك.
-Consort Yoo.
-Consort يو.  -Consort يو.
For this issue, please join forces with the meritorious subjects.
بالنسبة لهذه المشكلة ، يرجى توحيد الجهود مع الموضوعات الجديرة بالتقدير.
I promised Councilor Park that I will reduce his sentence
لقد وعدت كونسيلور بارك بأنني سوف أخفف عقوبته
in return for taking my true identity back.
مقابل استعادة هويتي الحقيقية.
Your Majesty.
جلالة الملك.
The consort's social status shakes the foundation of this nation.
الوضع الاجتماعي للقرين يهز أسس هذه الأمة.
We cannot condone this.
لا يمكننا التغاضي عن هذا.
Councilor Park confessed everything as his fault.
اعترف المستشار بارك كل شيء على أنه خطأه.
Why do you blame the consort?
لماذا تلوم القرين؟
So should we not hold her responsible for deceiving her superiors?
إذن ألا نحملها مسؤولية خداع رؤسائها؟
His Majesty condoned this and took a part in this.
وقد تغاضى جلالة الملك عن هذا وشارك في ذلك.
If you wish to hold her responsible, hold His Majesty responsible first.
إذا كنت ترغب في تحميلها المسؤولية ، فحمل جلالة الملك المسؤولية أولاً.
Then first, we must hold the late King responsible
ثم أولاً ، يجب أن نحمل الملك الراحل المسؤولية
for letting the consort live.
للسماح للقرين بالعيش.
And punishing the late King?
ومعاقبة الملك الراحل؟
That is unprecedented!
هذا غير مسبوق!
What should I do?
ماذا علي أن أفعل؟
Should I punish myself?
هل يجب أن أعاقب نفسي؟
Or should I punish the former King, my father?
أم أعاقب الملك السابق أبي؟
Your Majesty, please do not say that.
جلالة الملك ، من فضلك لا تقل ذلك.
We cannot discuss this issue anymore.
لا يمكننا مناقشة هذه المسألة بعد الآن.
But how astounding is this?
لكن ما مدى روعة هذا؟
The subjects and the Sarim are enemies, yet you two stand together.
الرعايا والساريم أعداء ، لكنكما تقفان معًا.
Councilor Park Gyewon is the one who caused everything.
المستشار بارك جيون هو الذي تسبب في كل شيء.
He'll be held responsible.
سيكون مسؤولا.
Father. It is I, your son.
أب.  أنا ابنك.
Come in.
ادخل.
Your Highness!
صاحب السمو!
Please spare my life, Your Highness.
أرجوك احتفظ بحياتي يا صاحب السمو.
-No! -Your Highness.
-رقم!  -صاحب السمو.
I received His Majesty's order to take Han and have her interrogated.
تلقيت أمر جلالة الملك بأخذ هان واستجوابها.
Take her away.
خذها بعيدا.
Your Highness.
صاحب السمو.
The King must be trying to annihilate everyone who's on my side.
لابد أن الملك يحاول إبادة كل من يقف بجانبي.
Your Highness!
صاحب السمو!
I will meet the King myself
سوف أقابل الملك بنفسي
and speak with him in person.
والتحدث معه شخصيًا.
THE KING'S QUARTERS
أرباع الملك
I beg you, Your Majesty.
أتوسل إليك يا صاحب الجلالة.
Please forgive your mother's sins.
من فضلك اغفر ذنوب والدتك.
Mother.
الأم.
Why are you doing this?
لماذا تفعل هذا؟
If I dishonored you in any way, please just lash me!
إذا كنت أهينك بأي شكل من الأشكال ، من فضلك فقط جلدني!
I heard the royal office
سمعت المكتب الملكي
has been chaotic every single day because of me.
كانت فوضوية كل يوم بسببي.
I wish to grovel and plead for your mercy.
أتمنى أن أتذلل وأطلب رحمتك.
Your Majesty, you must abandon me
جلالة الملك ، يجب أن تتخلى عني
and show your majesty.
وأظهر جلالتك.
That's enough.
هذا يكفي.
You are most unsightly.
أنت قبيح للغاية.
Will your subjects kill me
هل سيقتلني رعاياك
to save themselves?
لإنقاذ أنفسهم؟
Or…
أو…
will they begin a coup
هل سيبدأون انقلاب
and dethrone an undutiful son like you?
ويخلع عرش الابن الفاسد مثلك؟
No matter which side it is,
بغض النظر عن الجانب الذي هو عليه ،
there won't be any justification.
لن يكون هناك أي مبرر.
But if I hurt myself,
لكن إذا جرحت نفسي ،
their rebellion will be more justified.
سيكون تمردهم أكثر تبريرًا.
What must I do to apologize
ماذا علي أن أفعل لأعتذر
for my disobedience?
لعصيانى؟
Send me to the palace in Onyang along with my court ladies.
أرسلني إلى القصر في أونيانج مع سيدات بلادي.
I no longer have any strength to hold out in the palace.
لم يعد لدي أي قوة للصمود في القصر.
I will allow it,
سأسمح بذلك ،
Mother.
الأم.
The palace is filled with people who'll stab your back
القصر مليء بالأشخاص الذين يطعنون ظهرك
once you show them mercy.
بمجرد أن تظهر لهم الرحمة.
That is why I need someone who will absolutely take my side.
هذا هو السبب في أنني بحاجة إلى شخص سينحاز إلى جانبي تمامًا.
If they weren't with me,
إذا لم يكونوا معي ،
they were always against me.
كانوا دائما ضدي.
I will…
أنا سوف…
take your side and live with you
تأخذ جانبك وتعيش معك
until the end of my life.
حتى نهاية حياتي.
Then why are you doing this?
إذن لماذا تفعل هذا؟
Because I do not wish to lose you.
لأنني لا أتمنى أن أفقدك.
I am not your enemy, Your Majesty.
أنا لست عدوك يا جلالة الملك.
I wish to be a subject who gives you candid advice.
أتمنى أن أكون موضوعًا يقدم لك نصيحة صريحة.
Please accept me.
أرجو أن تقبلني.
You must accept me.
يجب أن تقبلني.
The Queen Dowager is leaving today.
الملكة الأرملة سترحل اليوم.
Your Majesty.
جلالة الملك.
I never expected the Sarim to collude
لم أتوقع قط أن يتواطأ الصريم
with the Royal Court.
مع الديوان الملكي.
If two enemies can work together,
إذا كان بإمكان اثنين من الأعداء العمل معًا ،
your subjects may work with the Queen Dowager again.
قد تعمل موضوعاتك مع الملكة الأرملة مرة أخرى.
I know that.
وأنا أعلم ذلك.
The Queen Dowager will be attacked by muggers
سيتم مهاجمة الملكة الأرملة من قبل اللصوص
on her way down to Onyang.
في طريقها إلى أونيانغ.
These are the same men who broke into the palace.
هؤلاء هم نفس الرجال الذين اقتحموا القصر.
When they weren't paid for their service, they decided to attack her out of grudge.
عندما لم يحصلوا على أجر مقابل خدمتهم ، قرروا مهاجمتها بدافع الضغينة.
I will make them confess that they killed the Queen Dowager.
سأجعلهم يعترفون بأنهم قتلوا الملكة الأرملة.
-Kyun. -This is the easiest way.
-Kyun.  -هذه الطريقة الأسهل.
You must take this path.
يجب أن تأخذ هذا الطريق.
Your Majesty.
جلالة الملك.
You must take the right path.
يجب أن تأخذ الطريق الصحيح.
I await your order.
أنا في انتظار طلبك.
Your Highness.
صاحب السمو.
We are ready to leave.
نحن على استعداد للمغادرة.
We should go.
علينا الذهاب.
All right.
حسنا.
You have
عندك
all done well.
كل شيء على ما يرام.
You may leave.
يمكنك المغادرة.
You need to stop.
أنت بحاجة إلى التوقف.
I must contemplate deeply on what I'll do with the Queen Dowager.
يجب أن أفكر بعمق في ما سأفعله مع الملكة الأرملة.
They'll arrive at the palace in Jinwi around tomorrow.
سيصلون إلى القصر في جينوي غدًا تقريبًا.
This is the Queen Dowager.
هذه هي الملكة الأرملة.
You must let her pass without pain.
يجب أن تدعها تمر دون ألم.
The Queen Dowager has left for the palace in Onyang?
الملكة الأرملة قد غادرت إلى القصر في أونيانغ؟
Yes, she put everything together quickly, so it wasn't even properly done.
نعم ، لقد جمعت كل شيء معًا بسرعة ، لذا لم يتم القيام بذلك بشكل صحيح.
When did she leave?
متي غادرت؟
About two days ago.
منذ حوالي يومين.
She'll probably stay at the palace in Jinwi today.
من المحتمل أن تبقى في القصر في جينوي اليوم.
She set her dwelling on fire to avoid getting pushed out.
أشعلت النار في مسكنها لتجنب دفعها للخارج.
On top of that, she knows she's a target of assassination.
علاوة على ذلك ، فهي تعلم أنها هدف اغتيال.
Yet she left the palace, the safest place for her?
ومع ذلك غادرت القصر ، أسلم مكان لها؟
I must leave immediately.
يجب أن أغادر على الفور.
No, my lord.
لا يا سيدي.
The only way is to break out of jail.
الطريقة الوحيدة هي الهروب من السجن.
Let me leave immediately!
اسمحوا لي أن أغادر على الفور!
Your Majesty, there is an urgent message.
جلالة الملك ، هناك رسالة عاجلة.
Come in.
ادخل.
YOUR MAJESTY
جلالتك
What is this?
ما هذا؟
The Queen Dowager left this letter for you.
تركت الملكة الأرملة هذه الرسالة لك.
When did she leave this?
متى تركت هذا؟
She has left two days ago.
لقد غادرت منذ يومين.
She told her adjunct overseer to give it to you after two days.
طلبت من مشرفها المساعد أن يعطيك إياه بعد يومين.
Eunuch Jung has not come in
لم يأتِ الخصي جونغ
since the day after the Queen Dowager has left.
منذ اليوم التالي لمغادرة الملكة الأرملة.
YOUR MAJESTY
جلالتك
Didn't I tell you, Your Majesty?
ألم أخبرك يا جلالة الملك؟
If I shed a drop of blood from my neck,
إذا سفكت قطرة دم من رقبتي
did you think you were safe on your throne?
هل كنت تعتقد انك على عرشك بمأمن؟
Once I die, there will be signs in my handwriting
بمجرد أن أموت ، ستكون هناك علامات في خط يدي
put up all over the country that says I was killed by you.
أقاموا في جميع أنحاء البلاد التي تقول إنني قتلت بواسطتك.
"The King…
"الملك…
has killed his mother."
قتل والدته ".
Your Majesty, I'm sure
جلالة الملك ، أنا متأكد
you will now want to save me from death.
الآن تريد أن تنقذني من الموت.
There is no stronger justification for the royal family to rebel against you.
لا يوجد مبرر أقوى للعائلة المالكة للتمرد عليك.
You'll become a child who killed his own mother.
ستصبح طفلاً قتل أمه.
I hope
آمل
you live in the pain I leave behind,
أنت تعيش في الألم الذي أتركه ورائي ،
caught up in bloody rebellion and purge.
محاصرين في التمرد الدموي والتطهير.
Send the cavalry guard to Jinwi Palace now.
أرسل حرس الفرسان إلى قصر جينوي الآن.
-Yes, Your Majesty. -Where's Eunuch Jung?
-نعم يا صاحب الجلالة.  -أين الخصي جونغ؟
Tell him to go to Jinwi Palace now,
قولي له أن يذهب إلى قصر جينوي الآن ،
that this is urgent!
أن هذا أمر عاجل!
Eunuch Jung has not come in since yesterday.
لم يأتِ الخصي جونغ منذ أمس.
Then where is he?
ثم أين هو؟
Did the King
فعل الملك
send you here?
ارسل لك هنا
Did you
هل فعلت
come to kill me?
تعال لقتلي؟
Shall I die for you?
هل أموت من أجلك؟
Once I die, you'll all live in pain.
بمجرد أن أموت ، ستعيشون جميعًا في ألم.
So I can gladly die for all of you.
لذلك يمكنني أن أموت بكل سرور من أجلكم جميعًا.
Your Highness.
صاحب السمو.
I am the reason…
انا السبب ...
for all of your sins.
عن كل ذنوبك.
So please,
إذن من فضلك،
you must live.
يجب أن تعيش.
Did the King tell you to make sure I live?
هل أخبرك الملك أن أتأكد من أنني أعيش؟
Your Joseon will stay as a whole only if I live,
ستبقى جوسون بك ككل فقط إذا عشت ،
so you finally want to save me now.
لذلك تريد أخيرًا إنقاذي الآن.
Were you so troubled?
هل كنت مضطرب جدا؟
Is that why
الهذا فعلت ذلك
you want to lay down everything?
تريد أن تضع كل شيء؟
You said you wanted to live as a housewife
قلت أنك تريد أن تعيش ربة منزل
who cooks dinner for her husband and wait for him to come home.
التي تطبخ العشاء لزوجها وتنتظر عودته إلى المنزل.
I forgot that
نسيت هذا
you were someone who could be happy
كنت شخصا يمكن أن يكون سعيدا
with the small things in life.
مع الأشياء الصغيرة في الحياة.
I should have let you live that life.
كان يجب أن أتركك تعيش تلك الحياة.
I regretted
ندمت
and regretted again.
وتأسف مرة أخرى.
Your Highness.
صاحب السمو.
Please live.
يرجى العيش.
Though life may be…
على الرغم من أن الحياة قد تكون ...
more humiliating and harsher…
أكثر إذلالا وأقسى ...
than death.
من الموت.
When flowers bloom,
عندما تتفتح الأزهار ،
you can look at those flowers
يمكنك إلقاء نظرة على تلك الزهور
and live a day…
وتعيش يوما ...
When it snows in the middle of winter,
عندما تتساقط الثلوج في منتصف الشتاء ،
you can look at the snow
يمكنك إلقاء نظرة على الثلج
and live yet another day.
وعيش يوم آخر.
When you live like that,
عندما تعيش هكذا ،
one day,
يوم واحد،
you will find yourself smiling once again.
ستجد نفسك تبتسم مرة أخرى.
Let me…
دعني…
Let me rest for a short while.
دعني أستريح لفترة قصيرة.
He died?
هو مات؟
Just like that?
مثل هذا تماما؟
Your Majesty.
جلالة الملك.
I must
يجب علي
leave the palace for a while.
اترك القصر لفترة.
What do you mean?
ماذا تقصد بذلك؟
The Central Army saw me.
رآني الجيش المركزي.
They will testify that
سوف يشهدون على ذلك
I killed Councilor Park
لقد قتلت كونسيلور بارك
and tried to kill the Queen Dowager.
وحاول قتل الملكة الأرملة.
In the meantime,
في هذه الأثناء،
it will be difficult for me to serve you.
سيكون من الصعب علي خدمتك.
It won't just be for a while.
لن يكون ذلك لفترة من الوقت فقط.
I will be within the city limits.
سأكون داخل حدود المدينة.
I will hide nearby
سأختبئ في مكان قريب
so that I can run to you whenever you need me.
حتى أتمكن من الركض إليك كلما احتجت إلي.
If you leave,
إذا غادرت ،
who am I supposed to trust?
من المفترض أن أثق؟
I asked the consort to look after you.
طلبت من الرفيق أن يعتني بك.
Just as the late King asked me to look after you,
مثلما طلب مني الملك الراحل أن أعتني بك ،
the only one I trust in this world
الوحيد الذي أثق به في هذا العالم
is the consort.
هو القرين.
Have you ever considered that your decisions were not right?
هل فكرت يومًا أن قراراتك لم تكن صحيحة؟
Do you have any intention
هل لديك أي نية
of asking for forgiveness
لطلب المغفرة
from the ones you killed, from my father?
من قتلتم من والدي؟
That will not
هذا لن يحدث
happen.
يحدث.
My enemy, the daughter of a rebel was queen.
كانت عدوي ابنة متمرد ملكة.
And the daughter of my political enemy, the Sarim,
وابنة عدوي السياسي صارم
became the crown princess.
أصبحت ولي العهد.
If I did not eliminate them first,
إذا لم أقضي عليهم أولاً ،
my people and my comrades
شعبي ورفاقي
would have died.
سيموت.
That is
هذا هو
politics.
سياسة.
I have come to visit.
لقد جئت للزيارة.
I will show you
سأريك
that my politics, my reign
أن سياستي ، عهدي
will take a different path than yours.
سيأخذ مسارًا مختلفًا عن طريقك.
IN MOURNING
في حالة حداد
You should not get up so soon.
يجب ألا تستيقظ قريبًا.
You lost consciousness for two days.
فقدت الوعي لمدة يومين.
Who served our guests in that while?
من خدم ضيوفنا في ذلك الوقت؟
Aunt stepped up.
صعدت العمة.
She's not well-trained in etiquette.
إنها ليست مدربة جيدًا على آداب السلوك.
We must have served our guests poorly as your father had passed.
يجب أن نكون قد خدمنا ضيوفنا بشكل سيء كما مات والدك.
Mother, you don't have to strain yourself.
أمي ، ليس عليك إجهاد نفسك.
I must do this.
يجب أن أفعل هذا.
I am the lady of this house,
انا سيدة هذا المنزل
who lived half of my life as the wife of the councilor.
التي عاشت نصف حياتي كزوجة المستشار.
Even though your father has passed,
على الرغم من وفاة والدك ،
that fact does not change.
هذه الحقيقة لا تتغير.
I have much to look after,
لدي الكثير لأعتني به ،
our family and the mouths to feed.
عائلتنا وأفواهنا نطعمها.
And you.
وأنت.
So I must remain strong.
لذلك يجب أن أبقى قويا.
I have won.
لقد فزت.
Your death
موتك
is humble indeed.
متواضع حقا.
All deaths
كل الوفيات
are humble.
متواضعون.
Your era has ended.
لقد انتهى عصرك.
This is now my era.
هذا هو الآن عهدي.
Do you believe your talent was overlooked
هل تعتقد أنه تم التغاضي عن موهبتك
because of your subjects?
بسبب مواضيعك؟
Do you not know that your subjects
ألا تعلم أن رعاياك
also help you cover up your faults?
تساعدك أيضا على التستر على أخطائك؟
I never asked you
لم أسألك قط
to cover up my faults.
للتستر على أخطائي.
From now on, your reign…
من الآن فصاعدا ، عهدك ...
is completely your responsibility.
هي مسؤوليتك بالكامل.
Do you believe…
هل تصدق…
I will manage well?
سوف أدير بشكل جيد؟
I do not know.
لا أعلم.
That is why
لذلك
I could not trust you.
لا أستطيع أن أثق بك.
However, your subjects are only here to give you advice.
ومع ذلك ، فإن الموضوعات الخاصة بك موجودة هنا فقط لتقديم المشورة لك.
All decisions are made
يتم اتخاذ جميع القرارات
by the sovereign ruler over our people,
من قبل الحاكم صاحب السيادة على شعبنا ،
according to your will, Your Majesty.
حسب إرادتك يا جلالة الملك.
Why do you cry?
لماذا تبكي؟
Now,
حاليا،
the one I must resent…
الشخص الذي يجب أن أستاء منه ...
is gone.
ذهب.
I will depose you.
سوف أقوم بخلعك.
It will become a long and tedious fight.
سوف تصبح معركة طويلة ومملة.
The people will be split for their own reasons.
الناس سينقسمون لأسبابهم الخاصة.
It'll take years to convince the officials
سوف يستغرق إقناع المسؤولين سنوات
and my people.
وشعبي.
Even after that, I will be criticized
حتى بعد ذلك ، سوف أتعرض للنقد
for dishonoring my parent until the end of my reign.
لإهانة والدي حتى نهاية عهدي.
However,
لكن،
it will be much better than seeing flyers around the country
سيكون أفضل بكثير من رؤية النشرات في جميع أنحاء البلاد
about how a son has killed his mother.
حول كيف قتل الابن والدته.
So please come with me,
لذا من فضلك تعال معي ،
back to the tormenting life
العودة إلى الحياة المعذبة
which you created.
الذي قمت بإنشائه.
Just…
فقط…
kill me.
اقتلني.
Your Majesty.
جلالة الملك.
Please.
لو سمحت.
Even if you hang yourself
حتى لو شنقت نفسك
or drink poison, I will save you.
أو أشرب السم سأخلصك.
I must show that the King is fulfilling his duty as a son.
يجب أن أبين أن الملك يؤدي واجبه كإبن.
So please continue to live
لذا من فضلك استمر في العيش
all alone in this palace
كل وحده في هذا القصر
and enjoy
و استمتع
a long life.
حياة طويلة.
Live a long life
عش حياة طويلة
all alone?
وحيد للغاية؟
What is this?
ما هذا؟
Isn't this a letter from Lady Jeong?
أليست هذه رسالة من الليدي جيونغ؟
Isn't it?
أليس كذلك؟
What's with all the fuss?
ما كل هذا العناء؟
-Take a look. -Okay, I'll look.
-إلق نظرة.  -حسنا ، سوف أنظر.
I'll look.
سأرى.
Are you teasing me?
هل تضايقني؟
You know I can't read.
أنت تعلم أنني لا أستطيع القراءة.
What did she say?
ماذا قالت؟
Is she well?
هل هي بخير؟
Is her mother-in-law nice to her?
هل حماتها لطيفة معها؟
She's well.
هي بخير.
-She asks if we're all well. -Goodness.
- تسأل إذا كنا جميعًا بخير.  -صلاح.
She thinks of all of you a lot.
هي تفكر بكم جميعاً كثيراً.
I hear there's an uproar in Hanyang.
سمعت أن هناك ضجة في هانيانغ.
Please don't go out and get in trouble.
من فضلك لا تخرج وتقع في مشكلة.
Make sure you stay home.
تأكد من البقاء في المنزل.
Okay?
تمام؟
Okay… Okay?
حسنا حسنا؟
Can you write that for me?
هل يمكنك كتابة ذلك لي؟
I hear the Queen Dowager is becoming something or whatever.
سمعت أن الملكة الأرملة أصبحت شيئًا أو أيا كان.
And that crown princess suddenly died, then came back alive.
وتوفي ولي العهد ذلك فجأة ، ثم عاد على قيد الحياة.
And who was it? That consort or something…
ومن كان؟  تلك القرينة أو شيء من هذا القبيل ...
Anyway, I can't believe there is so much trouble.
على أي حال ، لا أصدق أن هناك الكثير من المتاعب.
Everyone is talking about it.
الجميع يتحدث عن ذلك.
There's no use in giving advice here.
لا فائدة من إعطاء النصائح هنا.
She'll manage.
سوف تدير.
Lord Lim, you're really cold-hearted.
اللورد ليم ، أنت حقًا بارد القلب.
Goodness.
صلاح.
Hey.
يا.
You need me around here, don't you?
أنت بحاجة لي هنا ، أليس كذلك؟
What do you mean? You don't do anything around here.
ماذا تقصد بذلك؟  أنت لا تفعل أي شيء هنا.
I take care of the tributary payment and the things with the local government.
أنا أعتني بالدفع الإضافي والأشياء مع الحكومة المحلية.
That's not a big deal.
هذه ليست صفقة كبيرة.
If you aren't around, we'll still manage.
إذا لم تكن موجودًا ، فسنظل قادرين على ذلك.
We can go on even without Lady Jeong.
يمكننا الاستمرار حتى بدون السيدة جيونغ.
Why?
لماذا ا؟
Did the men up high in Hanyang ask you to come?
هل طلب منك الرجال في مكان مرتفع في هانيانغ أن تأتي؟
Will you go?
هل ستذهب؟
What will I do there anyway?
ماذا سأفعل هناك على أي حال؟
I'll end up seeing bureaucrats bickering one another,
سوف ينتهي بي الأمر برؤية البيروقراطيين يتشاجرون مع بعضهم البعض ،
instead of hearing our people.
بدلا من سماع شعبنا.
The noblemen who can listen to what we have to say
النبلاء الذين يمكنهم الاستماع إلى ما نقوله
keep avoiding such places out of disgust.
استمر في تجنب مثل هذه الأماكن بدافع الاشمئزاز.
That's why only those who won't listen to us remain there.
لهذا السبب فقط أولئك الذين لن يستمعوا إلينا يبقون هناك.
So?
لذا؟
Are you telling me to go?
هل تخبرني بالذهاب؟
Me?
أنا؟
Why do you do this to me?
لماذا تفعل هذا بي؟
How are you, master?
كيف حالك سيد؟
Is everyone well?
هل الجميع بخير؟
I see Bamboo Grove Village once in a while in my dreams.
أرى قرية بامبو جروف من حين لآخر في أحلامي.
The village holds dearly in my heart.
القرية عزيزة في قلبي.
Look at this.
انظر إلى هذا.
Although there are many, none are too wise.
على الرغم من وجود الكثير ، إلا أن لا أحد منهم حكيم للغاية.
So it is always a challenge.
لذلك فهو دائما تحد.
Please, be by my side in the palace.
من فضلك كن بجانبي في القصر.
Consort Yoo.
القرين يو.
Fifth Left Officer of the Ministry of Taxation is here.
الموظف الأيسر الخامس بوزارة الضرائب موجود هنا.
Fifth Left Officer Lim is here to report to Consort Yoo.
الضابط الأيسر الخامس ليم موجود هنا لتقديم تقرير إلى القرين يو.
I hear the Ministry of Taxation is busy,
سمعت أن وزارة الضرائب مشغولة ،
and it must be true.
ويجب أن يكون صحيحًا.
You came to the palace a while ago,
أتيت إلى القصر منذ فترة ،
but only come see me now.
لكن تعال فقط لتراني الآن.
I obtained my office thanks to the Left Minister,
حصلت على مكتبي بفضل الوزير الأيسر ،
so I focused on staying low
لذلك ركزت على البقاء منخفضًا
and doing my job the best I can.
وأقوم بعملي بأفضل ما يمكنني.
I'm glad you're here.
أنا سعيد لأنك هنا.
I heard you wanted to take the exam
سمعت أنك تريد إجراء الامتحان
instead of accepting the recommendation.
بدلا من قبول التوصية.
Many members of the Sarim have become officials,
أصبح العديد من أفراد صريم مسؤولين ،
which makes them other meritorious subjects,
مما يجعلهم مواضيع أخرى جديرة بالتقدير ،
and the harm they do is also quite troubling.
والضرر الذي يتسببون فيه مقلق للغاية أيضًا.
Is there a reason why you changed your mind?
هل هناك سبب غيرت رأيك؟
I began to feel the urgency.
بدأت أشعر بالإلحاح.
The crops continue to be bad. If we do not reduce labor and offerings,
المحاصيل لا تزال سيئة.  إذا لم نقلل من العمل والعروض ،
come next year, we will see even people in the city starving to death.
تعال العام المقبل ، سنرى حتى الناس في المدينة يتضورون جوعاً حتى الموت.
That is why
لذلك
I needed you, Master Lim.
كنت بحاجة لك ، سيد ليم.
Consort Yoo has…
القرينة يو لديها ...
Bring the royal physician at once!
أحضر الطبيب الملكي في الحال!
Your Majesty, Consort Yoo gave birth to a child.
جلالة الملك ، أنجبت قرينتك طفلاً.
How is she?
كيف حالها؟
Is she all right?
هل هي كل الحق؟
Yes, Your Majesty. She is healthy.
نعم يا صاحب الجلالة.  انها صحية.
Your Majesty, congratulations.
جلالة الملك ، مبروك.
-Congratulations.
-تهانينا.  -تهانينا.
Are you all right?
هل انت بخير؟
Yes.
نعم.
He's a boy.
انه صبي.
He looks…
يبدو…
really ugly.
حقا قبيحة.
He looks exactly like you.
هو يشبهك تماما
Do I look like this?
هل أبدو مثل هذا؟
Everyone complimented him and said he is a handsome boy.
أثنى عليه الجميع وقالوا إنه فتى وسيم.
Do you not think so?
ألا تعتقد ذلك؟
I do.
أفعل.
Would you like to hold him?
هل ترغب في حمله؟
I am your father.
انا والدك.
You've done well.
لقد قمت بعمل جيد.
You fool.
يالك من أحمق.
After creating a world where everything runs by your command,
بعد إنشاء عالم يعمل فيه كل شيء بأمرك ،
what will you do?
ماذا ستفعل؟
Are you confident that you will be different from a tyrant?
هل أنت واثق من أنك ستكون مختلفًا عن طاغية؟
Are the people by your side in this new world
هل الناس بجانبك في هذا العالم الجديد
genuinely loyal subjects…
موضوعات مخلصة بصدق ...
or are they treacherous?
ام هم غدرين؟
Minister Cho.
الوزير تشو.
Yes?
نعم؟
I need you to go into exile for a while.
أريدك أن تذهب إلى المنفى لفترة من الوقت.
The Minister of War became too big
أصبح وزير الحرب أكبر من اللازم
after our reorganization.
بعد إعادة تنظيمنا.
The Three Offices and the Sarim scholars petition every single day.
تقدم المكاتب الثلاثة وعلماء صارم التماسًا كل يوم.
What can I do?
ماذا يمكنني أن أفعل؟
Someone will have to be responsible.
شخص ما يجب أن يكون مسؤولا.
Was this
كان هذا
the end of my worth from the start?
نهاية قيمتي من البداية؟
What are the guards doing?
ماذا يفعل الحراس؟
Why is the commandant standing still?
لماذا القائد لا يزال قائما؟
How could I ever forget
كيف يمكن أن أنسى
that you were also a meritorious subject?
أنك كنت أيضًا موضوعًا جدير بالتقدير؟
I'll consider your contributions
سأفكر في مساهماتك
and won't punish you any further.
ولن يعاقبك أكثر.
What about Lady Cho?
ماذا عن السيدة تشو؟
She's a royal concubine I adore.
إنها محظية ملكية أعشقها.
She will be…
هي ستكون…
cared for.
اهتم ب.
I am grateful…
أنا ممنون…
for your mercy.
لرحمتك.
Didn't you want a subject that is absolutely loyal?
ألا تريد موضوعًا مخلصًا تمامًا؟
Instead of those who use all kinds of justifications to stop you,
بدلاً من أولئك الذين يستخدمون كل أنواع التبريرات لإيقافك ،
I can be more loyal to you.
يمكنني أن أكون أكثر ولاء لك.
So…
لذا…
why do you abandon me?
لماذا تتخلى عني
Father.
أب.
What are you stitching?
ماذا تخيط؟
It's a present for my sister-in-law once the baby is born.
إنها هدية لأخت زوجي بمجرد ولادة الطفل.
Why do you look after her?
لماذا تعتني بها؟
My silly brother is unsightly,
أخي السخيف قبيح ،
but what can I do? The baby will still be my nephew.
لكن ماذا افعل؟  سيظل الطفل ابن أخي.
Lady Cho.
سيدة تشو.
I must…
يجب علي…
travel far for a while.
السفر بعيدا لفترة من الوقت.
Where are you going?
إلى أين تذهب؟
Lady Cho!
سيدة تشو!
I will make my case with His Majesty!
سأدافع عن قضيتي مع جلالة الملك!
He cannot do this. He cannot do this to you!
لا يستطيع فعل هذا.  لا يستطيع أن يفعل هذا لك!
This is a process we must go through.
هذه عملية يجب أن نمر بها.
Why should you get exiled?
لماذا يجب أن يتم نفيك؟
Consort Yoo committed a crime,
ارتكبت القرينة يو جريمة ،
yet she continues to dwell here under the Sarim's protection.
ومع ذلك فهي لا تزال تسكن هنا تحت حماية ساريم.
Why should you go?
لماذا يجب ان تذهب؟
Is it because…
هل هذا بسبب…
I did not gain his favor?
أنا لم أحصل على مصلحته؟
No.
رقم.
I forgot for a moment
لقد نسيت للحظة
that His Majesty will not condone the domination of his wife's family.
أن جلالة الملك لن يتغاضى عن سيطرة أسرة زوجته.
Father…
أب…
The Sarim won't hold power forever.
الصارم لن يمسك بزمام السلطة إلى الأبد.
Hold out until their power dwindles.
انتظر حتى تتضاءل قوتهم.
His Majesty dismissed Minister Cho from his office
وأقال جلالة الملك الوزير تشو من منصبه
and sent him on an exile.
وأرسلوه إلى المنفى.
His Majesty drove out
قاد جلالة الملك
someone who could have taken his side.
شخص يمكن أن يأخذ جانبه.
Did you find out the sentiment of the Sarim in Yeongnam?
هل اكتشفت عاطفة ساريم في يونغنام؟
Do you really plan on using them?
هل حقا تخطط لاستخدامهم؟
Left Minister will protest violently.
وزير اليسار سوف يحتج بعنف.
I'll also need those in power who will hold my people in check.
سأحتاج أيضًا إلى من هم في السلطة والذين سيحكمون على شعبي.
Why did you come out this far?
لماذا خرجت إلى هذا الحد؟
You will fall into trouble if Consort Yoo finds out.
ستقع في مشكلة إذا اكتشفت القرينة يو ذلك.
His Majesty gave me his permission.
أعطاني جلالة الملك إذنه.
You must stay strong and hold out.
يجب أن تبقى قويا والصمود.
I will protect our family and our name.
سأحمي عائلتنا واسمنا.
I brought you up like this to let you live a comfortable life.
لقد ربيتك هكذا لأتيح لك أن تعيش حياة مريحة.
Do not do anything until the day I return.
لا تفعل أي شيء حتى يوم عودتي.
No.
رقم.
Even if I must beg His Majesty, I will lie with him.
حتى لو توجّهت إلى جلالة الملك ، فسأكذب معه.
I will bear him a son.
سوف أنجب له ابنا.
I will humor the consort if I must
سأقوم بالدعابة على القرين إذا كان لا بد من ذلك
and relieve you from your exile.
ويخلصك من منفاك.
I will build up enough strength so that no one dare
سوف أقوم ببناء قوة كافية حتى لا يجرؤ أحد
to hurt you or my brother.
ليؤذيك أو يؤذيك أخي.
I will protect you now,
سوف احميك الان
Father.
أب.
I may not be the queen,
قد لا أكون الملكة ،
but I shall become
لكني سأصبح
the Queen Dowager.
الملكة الأرملة.
I'd like to make Lady Cho a Noble Lady of rank junior one.
أود أن أجعل السيدة تشو سيدة نبيلة من رتبة صغرى.
I see.
أرى.
I shall adore Lady Cho and look after her.
سأعشق السيدة تشو وأعتني بها.
Before I do that,
قبل أن أفعل ذلك ،
I'd like to hold your installation
أود تعليق التثبيت الخاص بك
as the queen.
كملكة.
Your Majesty.
جلالة الملك.
From the moment I first met you,
منذ اللحظة الأولى التي التقيت فيها بك ،
I knew you were worthy of being the mother and a loyal subject of this nation.
علمت أنك تستحقين أن تكوني أماً ورضعة مخلصة لهذه الأمة.
That you're a woman who sees and knows
أنك امرأة ترى وتعرف
the things I overlook.
الأشياء التي أغفلت عنها.
"She'll prove to be useful, so I shall take her in."
"ستثبت أنها مفيدة ، لذا سأقبلها".
That's what I thought.
هذا ما اعتقدته.
If I had known you were such a frightening and mean subject…
لو كنت أعرف أنك موضوع مخيف ولئيم ...
If you did, you wouldn't have had me in the selection.
إذا فعلت ذلك ، فلن تكون لي في الاختيار.
Even if I knew,
حتى لو علمت ،
I would have done the same.
كنت سأفعل نفس الشيء.
It's a tough journey to stay together,
إنها رحلة صعبة للبقاء معًا ،
but it's still easier than losing you and the Prince.
لكنه لا يزال أسهل من خسارتك أنت والأمير.
Congratulations,
تهانينا،
Your Highness.
صاحب السمو.
Escorting you to the ceremony is my job as a royal concubine.
مرافقتك إلى الحفل هي وظيفتي كمحظية ملكية.
I'd like to escort you to the ceremony.
أود مرافقتك إلى الحفل.
Please allow me to do so.
من فضلك اسمح لي أن أفعل ذلك.
Thank you for your help.
شكرا لك على مساعدتك.
It's an honor.
انه لشرف.
Do you regret it?
هل انت نادم على ذلك؟
I already do.
أنا أفعل بالفعل.
You are a shimmering blade
أنت شفرة متلألئة
hanging above my head.
معلقة فوق رأسي.
They say there must be a sword hanging above
يقولون يجب أن يكون هناك سيف معلق فوقها
in order to feel the gravity of the throne.
ليشعروا بخطورة العرش.
You are my one and only sanctuary.
أنت ملاذي الوحيد.
I shall eternally be your sanctuary.
سأكون إلى الأبد ملاذك.
So I shall walk with you.
لذلك سوف أمشي معك.
For you are the sword above my head
لانك انت السيف فوق راسي
and my sanctuary.
وملاذى.
You are my lover,
أنت حبي،
my Queen,
ملكتي،
and…
و…
my political rival.
منافسي السياسي.
BLOODY HEART
قلب دموي
ON THE FIFTEENTH SOMEDAY
في اليوم الخامس عشر
Why do you stare so?
لماذا تحدق هكذا؟
To have a good long look at you.
لإلقاء نظرة فاحصة عليك.
It'll be another fifteen days till I can see you again.
سوف تمر خمسة عشر يومًا أخرى حتى أتمكن من رؤيتك مرة أخرى.
Translated by Eun-sook Yoon
ترجمه أون سوك يون